Hi, this is the women in data data-thon 2026 What's cooking.
RT in data for dinner, chose the track, with a focus on food insecurity.
Your chef, I'm sharing Brook team lead and project manager by day, data governance analysts.
I'm April Gillespie, a researcher, data scientist, GitHub manager. I'm a technical marketing engineer.
I'm Sandra Copecki, data discovery, data analyst, insight managers. So, I date, I'm
an IT specialist. I'm an IT specialist. Dashboarded in data analysts and
for work, I'm an IT data analyst. Our menu theme, the problem
statement. The women in data data thoughts main challenge is exploring the world's food systems through data from
farmed to for our team's focus is on food insecurity. Our scope, the globe, the United
States, the Southeast and Alabama, are home state. Food insecurity impacts families
and diminishes quality of life. Family space and uneven menu of limited access,
unafortability and under nourishment. We need community-driven solutions that deliver equitable food and
nourishment for all. The diners, our stakeholders, our local community and policy
makers, who are families, farmers and home growers, farmers market, local fishers,
and government levels of town, county, state, and federal. Next, the Chef's
Tools, our methodology and approach. For our food insecurity analysis, we use two primary data sources.
From the food and agriculture organization in the United Nations, we looked at global indicators, including moderate and
severe food insecurities, under nourishment and food unafortability across world regions. From feeding
America, we used U.S. and Alabama data. To prepare the meal, we used batch
downloads and merged our data set. We used Excel for analysis, by set up with met up chart for geographic
visualization, and tap low for the network. And like any kitchen,
we had a few miss happy. We originally wanted to focus more heavily on food access, but local level data was not consistently
available. So our story shifted toward food insecurity. We also wanted to explore the impact of food
allergies. That was an area we were passionate about, including, because acts of food does not necessarily mean
access to food that is safe for everyone. Unfortunately, the available data was not detailed enough to support
meaningful analysis we wanted to do. So we made the decision not to force a conclusion the data could
not support. Our first course is the appetizer of global food insecurity.
Global food insecurity reflects a world where billions face limited access to nutritious affordable diet,
despite overall increases in food availability, driven by unequal distribution, fighting course,
and heavy dependence on fragile supply chain. Globally, millions experience moderate and severe food insecurity
due to poverty and other factors. Nick Horses the soup of the United
States food insecurity is defined by the USDA as a household level economic and social
condition of limited or uncertain access to adequate food. U.S. food insecurity reflects a nation
with abundant food supply, but uneven access and affordability, where million, especially in low-income
and rural communities, struggle to obtain consistent nutritious diet, despite high-national availability.
Food insecurity is often linked to multiple factors creating a cycle that can be difficult to break.
Nick Horses, salad of the United States, South East, food insecurity and the U.S. Southeast were
like a region where structural, poverty, limited food access, high price, sensitivity, and climate vulnerability
combined to produce some of the nation's highest or most persistent rates of inconsistent access to nutritious
food. The main course is, next, of Alabama, food insecurity.
Alabama's food insecurity reflects the state where nutritious food is unevenly at a access and increasingly
unaffordable with rural isolation, concentrated poverty, limited fresh food retail, and climate-driven
production instability creating persistent, region-specific vulnerability, despite overall national abundant.
Alabama faces significant disparities in low access and low income with some of the counties experiencing extreme
levels of both. For dessert, we have some pretty sweet solutions for local communities.
These solutions are practical and leverage resources are already present and available with thin communities causing
cost effectiveness. These solutions being supporting local food pantries, supporting local
shelters, having a small food pantry in the solve of a library that provides non-perishable staples,
local communities small buses, acting like fresh pantries, as well as supporting farmers and fishers.
After dinner coffee or future work, though we were unable to analyze the effects of allergies on food
insecurity, we let out needs if we were to do so. There would need to be continued research,
expanded data discovery, deeper insights into affordability, access and nutrition, especially
considering food allergy constraints and local crop availability. We also identified
the top food allergens specific to Alabama due to sourcing,
enclosing our teen research for main takeaways. One, food insecurity is a multi-scale
systems challenge that becomes clear when analyzed through integrated data-driven geospatial methods
to structural instability, economic stop, and limited food systems resilience
create widespread mobility. Three, rule isolation, unlimited food, retail infrastructure,
and tons of food and security. And lastly, findings highlight the value of layered geospatial analysis
by identifying actual intervention points and support a practical framework of low-cost scalable
solution. If you would like to dive deeper into our analysis, you can either visit
our Get a hug, repository, or if you are a table of public dashboard.